Guide to the Peter Newell Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter Newell collection
1895-1907
YCAL MSS 63
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(5 boxes)
The collection contains 35 drawings by illustrator Peter Newell which were acquired by the library, either by purchase or gift, primarily through funds left to the library by Newell's grandson Alfred Z. Baker (1907-1987). They include illustrations created for the Harper and Brothers firm and their periodicals Harper's Weekly, Harper's Monthly, and Harper's Bazar; illustrations created for other publishers; and examples of Newell's personal artwork, such as a self-portrait and portraits of his wife and son.
Newell, Peter, 1862-1924
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Drawings in Series I were purchased from James Cummins on the Alfred Z. Baker Fund; Series II were purchased from Heritage Book Shop, Inc. on the Jockey Hollow Fund; Series III were purchased from Jo Ann Reisler, Ltd. on the Alfred Z. Baker, Jr. Fund; Series IV was the gift of Adele Zachrisson; Series V, VI, and VII were purchased from James Arsenault & Company on the Alfred Z. Baker Fund.
Associated Materials
The Peter Newell Family Papers (YCAL MSS 62) contains personal and business correspondence, drawings, personal papers, photographs, and family material related to the artist and his career.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Peter Newell (1862-1924)
Peter Newell, an illustrator and author, was born in Illinois and lived in and around New York City for most of his life. Extensive information on Newell and his career appears in the finding aid for the Peter Newell Family Papers (YCAL MSS 62).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains 35 drawings by the artist Peter Newell which were acquired by the library, either by purchase or gift, primarily through funds left to the library by Newell's grandson Alfred Z. Baker (1907-1987). They include illustrations created for the Harper and Brothers firm and their periodicals Harper's Weekly, Harper's Monthly and Harper's Bazar; illustrations created for other publishers; and examples of Newell's personal artwork such as a self-portrait, and portraits of his wife and son.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series: I. Drawings acquired 1994 (1895-1909); II. Addition, 2004 (undated); III. Addition, 2005 (1914); IV. Addition, 2006 (undated); V. Addition, 2007 (1894-1902); VI. Addition, 2008 (1893-1899); VII. Addition, 2009 (undated).
Caricatures and cartoons; Children -- Pictorial works; Christmas -- Caricatures and cartoons; Illustrators -- United States -- 19th century; Magazine illustration -- United States; Portraits; Self-portraits; Spanish-American War, 1898 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Watercolors (paintings) -- United States; Illustrators -- United States; Bangs, John Kendrick, 1862-1922 ( House-boat on the Styx); Bangs, John Kendrick, 1862-1922 ( Pursuit of the house-boat); Newell, Clendenon Sheaf, 1892-1918 -- Portraits; Newell, Leona Dow Ashcraft, 1861-1954 -- Portraits; Newell, Peter, 1862-1924 -- Portraits; Newell, Peter, 1862-1924; Sampson, William Thomas, 1840-1902 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Stockton, Frank R., 1834-1902 ( Great stone of Sardis); Washington, Augustine, approximately 1694-1743 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Washington, George, 1732-1799 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Harper & Brothers; Harper, Lillie Hyde, 1881-1941 -- Ownership
- Drawings (acquired 1994), 1895-1909; Series I; 0.25; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of seventeen drawings commissioned by Harper and Brothers, over half of which were made to accompany two serialized stories by John Kendrick Bangs, "A House-boat on the Styx" and "The Pursuit of the House-Boat," which were later published as novels. Another set of drawings was made for the Frank Stockton serial story, "The Great Stone of Sardis," which was also published in book form. Two other illustrations for serialized stories are included, as is a single example of a Peter Newell comic. The drawings are arranged by the author of the story illustrated, with the single comic by Newell filed under his authorship. Page numbers following the title of a drawing refer to the location of the illustration as it appeared in the novel.
  - Bangs, John Kendrick
    - "A House-boat on the Styx"
      Published in Harper's Weekly and afterward as a novel by Harper and Brothers (1896)
      - "Lord Bacon, accompanied by Charon, appeared" (p. 24), 1895 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - "Doctor Johnson in a rage" (p. 48), 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "The melancholy Dane appeared" (p. 52), 1895 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "Ejecting a frenzied poet from the card-room" (p. 58), 1895 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "The house-committee discuss the poets" (p. 64), 1895 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "Boy, is Adam in the club-house today?" (p. 80), 1895 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Pursuit of the House-boat"
      Published in Harper's Weekly and afterward as a novel by Harper and Brothers (1897)
      - "Every bloomin' million was represented by a certified check, an' payable in London" (p. 84), 1897 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - "Queen Elizabeth desires an axe and one hour of her olden power" (p. 90), 1897 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - "The committee on treachery is ready to report" (p. 102), 1897 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - "Shem in the lookout" (p. 128), 1897 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - "Kidd's companions endeavoring to restore evaporated portions of his anatomy with a steam-atomizer" (p. 154), 1897 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newell, Peter
    - "Some former residents of New York, while revisiting the glimpses of the moon on New-Year's Eve, meet with a surprise on the Bowery" for Harper's Monthly, 1901 Jan (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Stockton, Frank
    - "The Great Stone of Sardis"
      Published in Harper's Monthly and afterward as a novel by Harper and Brothers (1898)
      - "Under the great skylight" (p. 36), 1897 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - "There's whales in this polar sea" (p. 110), 1897 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - "They ceased operations" (p. 154), 1897 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Stuart, Ruth McEnery
    - "The Haunted Photograph"
      Published in Harper's Bazar and afterward as a novel by The Century Company (1911)
      - "She succumbed, green as the Ganges, into her own egg-basket" (p. 18), 1909 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Unknown author
    - "The End of the Flying-Dutchman"
      - "Portrait of my grand-father", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Addition (2004), undated; Series II; 2
  The series consists of sketches for two holiday-themed cartoon drawings which were likely created for one of the Harper Brothers' magazines.
  - [Cupid and a frog], ink and watercolor on paper mounted on paperboard, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    General note
    Cupid, in gray overcoat, waves at frog in water; inscribed "To Mrs. William Ostler, faithfully yours, Peter Newell"
  - [Young George Washington], ink and pencil on paper mounted on card stock, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    The image shows a boy, presumably representing a young George Washington, standing next to a fallen tree and an axe, facing his father. Includes caption: "'Oh, father dear, I cannot tell - I cannot tell a lie. It--' 'Then, George, my son, if I were you, indeed, I wouldn't try it.'"
- Addition (2005), 1914; Series III; 2
  The series consists of two drawings, one humorous cartoon and one that was presented as a mechanical toy used to illustrate a story.
  - "A Class in Geography," ink on paper mounted on paperboard, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    A bearded elf instructing four elf children in a geography lesson, using the patterns on the side of a Holstein cow to represent a map.
  - "The pumpkin opened and closed its eyes in a mysterious way," from the series "Peter Newell's Movies" in The Delineator, ink and gouache on paper mounted on paperboard, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Number 2 of 4 images published in October 1914 (p. 33); see YCAL MSS 62, box 57, folders 937-938 for drawings 1 and 4, and box 242, folder 3329 for tearsheet.
- Addition (2006), undated; Series IV
  The series consists of a single drawing, a self-portrait showing the artist in bust profile. It is inscribed to Miss Emily Dawes, the maternal great-aunt of the donor.
  - Self-portrait, ink and watercolor on paper, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Addition (2007), 1894-1902; Series V; 5
  The series consists of five drawings: two have a Christmas theme; one is a page from a calendar designed by Newell; one is an illustrated rhyme; and the fifth is a portrait of the artist's son Clen.
  - "I wish you 'Merry Xmas'," pencil, ink, and watercolor on paperboard, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Image shows a small boy posited between two Christmas trees, accompanied by a verse.
  - "Little Mary Christmas," pencil, ink, and watercolor on paperboard, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Image shows a doll or girl posited in a wreath, accompanied by a verse.
  - Clendenon Sheaf Newell (1892-1918), pencil and watercolor on paper mounted on paperboard, 1894 Jun 21 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - "July," from his calendar for 1903, ink and watercolor on paperboard, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    See YCAL MSS 62, box 120, folders 1535-1536, for the preliminary pencil sketch and finished drawing for the calendar page
  - "A Young Hero," ink on paper mounted on paperboard, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Image shows a small boy and a snake; includes caption: "Brave Lambeth Jones encountered, by the trolley in the lane, A dreadful wriggling live wire, and he killed it with his cane."
- Addition (2008), 1893-1899; Series VI; 7
  The series consists of seven drawings, five of which were cartoons produced for one of the Harper magazines, and on their versos bear an ownership label (likely related to exhibition loans) of Lillie Harper (1881-1941), a New York sculptor who was the great-granddaughter of James Harper, founder of Harper Brothers publishing company. The sixth was published in Collier's Weekly, in a series of humorous cartoons about of the Spanish-American War, and the seventh is a portrait of Newell's wife Leona.
  - "A Christmas Allegory," ink, watercolor, and china white on paper mounted on paperboard, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Published in Harper's Magazine (January 1894) and in Peter Newell's Pictures and Rhymes (1899); formerly owned by Lillie Harper. Includes caption: "Spake Phoebe Jones in clearest tones, 'Permit me, Sir and Madame--I represent a Christmas Eve, and Will-a Christmas Adam!'"
  - [The Duck and the stork], ink and china white on paper mounted on paperboard, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    Published in Harper's Round Table; formerly owned by Lillie Harper. Includes caption: "The Duck.- 'Say, are you going to hang up your stocking on Christmas Eve?' The Stork.- 'Naw, I want something more than a tooth-pick!'"
  - [Grasshopper], ink and china white on paper mounted on paperboard, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Possibly published in Harper's Round Table; formerly owned by Lillie Harper.
  - Leona Dow Newell (1861-1954), ink and china white on paper mounted on paperboard, 1896 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - "A Suggestion that Admiral Sampson Should Use the 'Vesuvius' with Discretion," gouache on paperboard, 1898 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Caricature of Admiral William T. Sampson, published in Collier's Weekly (July 2, 1898) as number 4 in Newell's series "The Humorous Side of the War."
  - ["An Unreasonable Complaint"], ink and china white on paper mounted on paperboard, 1896 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Published in Harper's Round Table and Peter Newell's Pictures and Rhymes (1899); formerly owned by Lillie Harper. Includes caption: "The Sheep.-'Whew! But it is hot!' The Boy.- 'I should think it would be. You haven't taken off your woolens yet.'"
  - "Washington Maketh Love," ink and china white on paper mounted on paperboard, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Possibly published in Harper's Bazar; formerly owned by Lillie Harper. Includes caption: "In vain have foemen shot at me with rifle ball and dart. But, oh, your glances, Martha, dear, have pierced me to the heart!"
- Addition (2009), undated; Series VII
  The series consists of one pencil sketch to illustrate an unidentified story.
  - [Queen watches as cat runs under throne], pencil on paper mounted on paperboard, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)